Finding Aid for Mary P. Sinclair papers, 1967-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary P. Sinclair papers 1967-1999
Sinclair, Mary P.
37 linear feet
85380 Aa 2
Lecturer, writer, and consultant on energy and environmental subjects, most notably the uses and hazards of nuclear energy. Correspondence; her statements, articles, and letters to newspaper editors; reference files; conference and consultation materials; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mary Sinclair (donor no. 5569 ) beginning in 1981. Periodic additions have been received.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Mary P. Sinclair was born September 23, 1918, in Chisholm, Minnesota. In 1940, she graduated from the College of St. Catherine (St. Paul, MN), majoring in chemistry and English. During the 1950s, she worked at the Library of Congress. There she first became interested in the problems of nuclear energy as a result of her work with classified material from the Atomic Energy Commission.
After moving to her husband's hometown of Midland, Michigan, Sinclair worked as a librarian and technical writer for the Dow Chemical Corporation until retiring to devote her time to raising her children. Her concern about nuclear energy continued, however, and in 1967, when Consumers Power announced plans to construct a nuclear plant in Midland, Sinclair began publicly questioning the move and writing critical letters to the Midland Daily News.
Despite the hostile reactions of other Midland residents, Sinclair escalated her fight against the nuclear plant in 1969, forming the Saginaw Valley Nuclear Study Group, which intervened as a party to the Atomic Energy Commission hearings on the plant. In 1972, she helped to organize National Intervenors, a coalition of anti-nuclear groups designed to intervene in hearings on nuclear safety. Sinclair earned an M.S. in environmental communications from the University of Michigan in 1973. From 1974 to 1978, she held the position of lecturer at the University of Michigan.
Sinclair has participated in numerous conferences on nuclear and environmental issues sponsored by such organizations as the Great Lakes Basin Commission, the Federal Energy Administration, and the United Auto Workers. She has been a member of the National Energy Policy Committee of the Sierra Club, which she represented at the World Energy Conference in Detroit in 1974. In 1978, Sinclair organized the Great Lakes Energy Alliance.
Sinclair's seventeen-year fight against the Consumers Power nuclear plant ended when Consumers Power canceled the plant in 1984. Shortly thereafter, she began working to end Michigan's involvement in the Midwest Compact, the result of the Radioactive Waste Policy Act of 1980 and its 1985 amendment which named Michigan as a dumping ground for low-level radioactive waste. In March 1988, Sinclair helped organize Don't Waste Michigan, a group dedicated to this issue. Michigan eventually withdrew from the Compact.
Sinclair earned her Ph.D. from the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources in 1991. Since receiving her Ph.D., Sinclair has actively opposed dry cask storage of high-level radioactive waste, especially near the Lake Michigan shore. She was also involved in considering issues relating to the clean-up of nuclear waste following the closing of Big Rock Nuclear Plant in 1997.
The Mary Sinclair collection provides detailed documentation of one woman's grassroots battle against nuclear power plants in Michigan. The collection, which was received in multiple accessions, has been arranged into the following series: Biographical and honors; Correspondence; Writings and speeches; People file; Early files; Citizen groups; Great Lakes Energy Alliance; University of Michigan; Government agencies; Midland Plant; Palisades Plant; Industries; Radiation; Alternatives to nuclear fission; Mass media; Topical files; Other cases; and Audio-visual material. The files contain both original and collected materials on topics related to her anti-nuclear activities.
Subjects:
Antinuclear movement--Michigan.; Nuclear energy--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Nuclear power plants--Environmental aspects--Michigan.; Nuclear power plants--Michigan.; Sinclair, Mary P.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Activists.; Atomic power.; Chemical industry--Michigan--Midland.; Dow Chemical Company.; Midland (Mich.)--Chemical industry.; Nuclear reactors.; Sinclair, Mary P.
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Biographical and Honors 1970-1995
  The Biographical and Honors series (0.5 lin. ft.) contains documents relating to profiles of Sinclair which have appeared on 60 Minutes, and in the Wall Street Journal and Ms. Magazine, as well as scholarly papers written by individuals researching Sinclair's role in the environmental movement. Producer Chris Weicher's research files pertaining to the 60 Minutes program document events which Sinclair herself judged most important for her biography. This series also includes transcripts of interviews with Sinclair and several versions of her resumes.
  - Vita (Box 19)
  - Clippings (Box 19)
  - 60 Minutes
    - "Mary and Goliath" Script January 27, 1985 (Box 19)
    - Producer Chris Weicher's Notes 1984 (Box 19)
    - Producer Weicher's Research 1984, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Reaction to story 1985-1986 (Box 19)
  - Articles about Sinclair 1974-1992 (Box 19)
  - Briskin, Fred, re: "The Mary Sinclair Story," 1985-1988 (Box 19)
  - Charred remains of letter from bombed mailbox 1983 (Box 19)
  - Detroit News Award: Michiganians of the Year, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Distelheim, Rochelle
    - Article on Mary Sinclair 1985 (Box 19)
    - Transcript of Interview with Mary Sinclair 1985 (Box 19)
  - Ellicott-Black Award--American Ethical Union 1985 (Box 19)
  - Family 1970-1994 (Box 19)
  - Frantilla, Anne
    - "The Point at Which You Become a Citizen: Mary Sinclair and the Midland Nuclear Power Plant," 1985 (Box 19)
    - Transcript of Interview with Mary Sinclair March 29, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Ginsberg, Andrew D. "Selected Regulatory and Class Issues in the Matter of the Midland Nuclear Power Controversy," 1981 (Box 19)
  - Groundwork for a Just World testimonial dinner May 2, 1993 (Box 19)
  - Home for Peace and Justice banquet March 28, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Joe A. Calloway Award for Civic Courage 1992 (Box 19)
  - Johnson, M. Rene, "Nuclear Power vs. the People's Power: Three Strikes and You're Out?" 1995 (Box 19)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame 1990 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous awards 1978-1990 (Box 19)
  - Ms. Magazine: "12 Women of 1984" 1985 (Box 19)
  - Personal goals 1987 (Box 19)
  - Radio Heaven: A play about College of St. Catherine, 1992 (Box 19)
  - Resumes undated (Box 19)
  - United Nations Conference for New and Renewable Sources of Energy for the Third World, Nairobi 1981 (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan PhD May, 1992 (Box 19)
  - Wall Street Journal Article 1984 (Box 19)
- Correspondence 1967-1999
  Correspondence (3.5 lin. ft.) is arranged into two subseries, first by date, and second by subject/correspondent. Sinclair's files contain not only incoming letters, but also copies of her replies. Correspondents include other citizen activists such as Christa-Maria, Kay Drey, Gerald and Martha Drake, Billie Garde, and Helen LeTarte. Researchers seeking information about these individuals should consult files in the "People File" series as well.
  Nearly one box of this material is related to Sinclair's 1992-1994 correspondence with Fawn Shillinglaw, an anti-nuclear activist who resided in Appleton, Wisconsin and shared her research on dry cask storage of nuclear waste with Sinclair. This material supported the Kelley v. Selin lawsuit. Other files document correspondence with politicians and industry officials.
  - By date
    - Undated, 1967, 1969-1984, 29 folders (Box 1)
    - 1984-1992, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - 1992-1999, 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous categories of correspondents circa 1970-1996
    - Attorneys (Box 19)
    - Businesses and industries (Box 19)
    - Colleges and universities, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Congressmen and Senators, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Detroit Free Press (Kurt Leudtke) (Box 19)
    - Flint Journal (Box 19)
    - General correspondence, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Kalamazoo Nature Center (Lewis Batts) (Box 20)
    - National agencies (Box 20)
    - News media, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Orders; requests for information, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - State of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - By name of individual/organization
    - Asperger, Robert G. 1972-1974 (Box 20)
    - Calvin, Melvin 1978 (Box 20)
    - Christa-Maria 1979-1980 (Box 20)
      (See also Big Rock files)
    - Davis-Anthony, Vernice, Director, Mich. Dept. of Public Health 1992 (Box 20)
    - Denton, Harold, Director, Office of Nuclear Reactor Regulation 1981 (Box 20)
    - Dingell, Rep. John 1983-1993 (Box 20)
    - Donley, John P. 1977-1980, undated (Box 20)
    - Dow Chemical/Sierra Club 1981 (Box 20)
    - Dow re: Ecology Paper 1971-1972 (Box 20)
    - Drake, Martha and Gerald 1978-1992, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Drey, Kay 1980-1988 (Box 20)
    - Fetter, Steven, Chairman, Mich. Public Services Commission 1992-1993 (Box 20)
    - Garde, Billie, Government Accountability Project 1982-1985 (Box 20)
    - Hoffman, Philip, State Senator 1993 (Box 20)
    - Kelley, Frank, Attorney General of Michigan 1983-1996 (Box 20)
    - Kilpatrick, Norman, Surface Mining Research Library 1984 (Box 20)
    - LeTarte, Helen 1981-1985 (Box 20)
    - Levin, Senator Carl 1992-1993 (Box 21)
    - MacLeod, Gordon K., Univ. of Pittsburgh 1980-1982 (Box 21)
    - Pollack, Senator Lana 1988-1989 (Box 21)
    - Reinke Construction 1989 (Box 21)
    - Reizen, Maurice S., Mich. Dept. of Public Health 1977 (Box 21)
    - Shillinglaw, Fawn 1992-1994, 10 folders (Box 21)
    - Soderstrom, Dr. Robert 1992-1994 (Box 21)
    - Standard & Poor's Corp. 1982 (Box 21)
    - Taylor, Dorothy 1982-1985 (Box 21)
- Writing and Speeches 1967-1997
  The Writing and Speeches series (1.8 lin. ft.) contains Sinclair's articles, letters to the editor, statements before legislative bodies, and speeches, as well as copies of unpublished sources and interview transcripts her work relies upon. In the original accession (Box 2), her works are individually foldered and arranged by date. Sinclair's works in the later accessions (Boxes 21 and 22) are gathered together in chronological files, except for those works which have additional supporting documentation, which are separately foldered. There is significant chronological overlap between the two accessions.
  - Writings 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - "Decision-Making about Nuclear Technology," undated (Box 2)
  - "Will Nuclear Power Solve Michigan's Energy Crisis?" undated (Box 2)
  - "Statements and Questions on Nuclear Power and Public Concern," May, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Testimony before the Michigan Public Service Commission December 3, 1969 (Box 2)
  - "Nuclear Power and Public Concern," pamphlets 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Michigan Water Resources Commission Hearing August 10, 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Nuclear Power-The Facts You Haven't Been Told," speech September 29, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Statement on the need for better funding for nuclear fusion before the U.S. House and Senate subcommittee on Public Works May 19, 1971 (Box 2)
  - "The AEC Licensing Hearing Intervention--The Route to Nuclear Responsibility," speech November 4, 1971 (Box 2)
  - "Social Values and Nuclear Power in Modern Society," lecture November 9, 1972 (Box 2)
  - News Release March 22, 1973 (Box 2)
  - "The Social Impact of Nuclear Power," seminar presentation June 29, 1973 (Box 2)
  - MEA article for Teacher's Voice, submitted December 27, 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Nuclear Energy Policy Ignores Public Risk," article in Michigan Daily, January 26, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Commission of the Department of Natural Resources April 11, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Michigan Public Service Commission September 5, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Statement on Nuclear Power Moratorium for Michigan, before the Michigan House Chambers October 24, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Statement for the National Science Foundation "Science for Citizens" Program January 8, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Council of Environment Quality September 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Commission of the Department of Natural Resources March 11, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Statement before the Michigan Public Service Commission on the need to make evacuation plans known to the public May 3, 1976 (Box 2)
  - "Save the Valley," speech May 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - NEMCOG hearing statement October 21, 1976 (Box 2)
  - "Is Nuclear Power the Best Energy Resource for the Future?", speech October 30, 1976 (Box 2)
  - "A Critique of the CED Report Nuclear Energy and National Security," November 20, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Comments on Nuclear Waste Management Reports November 22, 1976 (Box 2)
  - "Nuclear Critics Regroup," article in Midland Daily News, April 28, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Statement: "Goals for a Michigan Department of Energy," June 7, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Statement at Midland N-Plant Rally November 18, 1978 (Box 2)
  - "Unresolved Public Health and Safety Issues at Midland N-Plants...," news release December 14, 1978 (Box 2)
  - "The Mounting Costs of Nuclear Power," speech May 2, 1979 (Box 2)
  - "Proposal for a Fact-Finding Study on Nuclear Power...," September, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Earth Day statement April 22, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Letters to the editor, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Thesis, "Nuclear Power Environmental Communications--A Case Study," University of Michigan School of Natural Resources 1973 (Box 2)
  - Thesis, "Nuclear Power Environmental Communications--A Case Study" (cont.) (Box 3)
  - Chronological 1969-1984, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Chronological 1995-1997, undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - "Control of Press in Company Town: Results of Whitewash of Critical Nuclear Plant Issues," 1971 (Box 22)
  - "International Industrial Effort in Pollution Control and Product Stewardship," 1971
    (Paper for Prof. Stanley Cain's Human Ecosystems course)
    - Paper (Box 22)
    - Interview transcripts
      - R.A. Gaska 1971 (Box 22)
      - Ted Ilgenfritz 1971 (Box 22)
      - Chet Otis 1971 (Box 22)
      - E.S. (Bud) Shannon 1971 (Box 22)
    - Unpublished references 1971, 2 folders (Box 22)
      (Dow Chemical's research papers on environmental effects of products)
    - Dow Environmental PR 1971 (Box 22)
  - Letters to the Editor manuscripts 1977-1982 (Box 22)
  - PhD Thesis
    - "The Role of Citizen Public Interest Groups in the Decision-Making Process of a Science-Intensive Culture," 1991 (Box 22)
    - Research documents: Midland Case (Box 22)
  - Radio Commentary 1982 (Box 22)
  - "Statement for Public Meeting on High Level Nuclear Waste Storage in an Untested Concrete Cask System at Palisades Nuclear Plant," 1993 (Box 22)
  - Statements on Low Level Radioactive Waste 1984-1985 (Box 22)
- People File 1968-1977
  The People File (1.2 lin. ft.) series contains a variety of materials, such as clippings, speeches and articles by and concerning the subject, correspondence to and from the subject, and legal pleadings and documents associated with that person.. The material in this series derives entirely from the first accession. In the later accessions (beginning after Box 19), material regarding individuals may be located in the Correspondence or Topical files series.
  - Asperger, Robert 1970-1977 (Box 3)
  - Banner, Paul undated (Box 3)
  - Batts, Lewis 1972-1977 (Box 3)
  - Benda, Robert S. 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Bibliography information 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Bjerke, Kathleen 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Bloomer, Christie 1976 (Box 3)
  - Cederberg, Elford A.,1976 (Box 3)
  - Cherry, Myron M. 1970-1977, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Clawson, Patrick 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Caghan, Paul 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Cramton, Louis 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Cutler, Rupert 1975 (Box 3)
  - Cudd, Montie 1977 (Box 3)
  - Doan, H. D.(Ted) 1973 (Box 3)
  - Doyle, Shirley 1974 (Box 3)
  - Drake, Gerald 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Drake, Martha 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Edison Company 1975-1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Evans, Vicki 1971 (Box 4)
  - Environmental News 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Friedman, Saul 1973 (Box 4)
  - Geesaman, Donald 1976 (Box 4)
  - Gofman, John 1972-1975 (Box 4)
  - Gravel, Mike 1972 (Box 4)
  - Griffin, Robert, U.S. Senator 1970 (Box 4)
  - Hammond, R. Philip 1974 (Box 4)
  - Hart, Philip, U.S. Senator 1970 (Box 4)
  - Holcomb, Larry 1972 (Box 4)
  - Huntington, Morgan 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Huver, Charles 1974 (Box 4)
  - Kikuchi, C. 1973 (Box 4)
    (U. of M. Professor of Nuclear Engineering)
  - Lanouette, William 1973 (Box 4)
  - Muntzing, L. Manning 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Nader, Ralph 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Pastore, John 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Proxmire, William, U.S. Senator 1972 (Box 4)
  - Radford, Edward P. 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Rasmussen, Norman 1974 (Box 4)
  - Reiner, Hans 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - Reynolds, Martha 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Richardson, Robert, Mich. Senator 1971 (Box 4)
  - Rosenberg, William, Chair PSC 1975 (Box 4)
  - Ross, Marc 1973 (Box 4)
    (U. of M. Professor of Physics)
  - Ryan, William A., Speaker of Mich. House 1974 (Box 4)
  - Steketee, Peter W. 1971 (Box 4)
  - Wolpe, Howard, Mich. Rep. 1976 (Box 4)
- Early files circa 1969-1971
  The Early Files series (1.5 lin. ft.) contains files from the beginning of Sinclair's career as an activist. Correspondence, articles, legal papers, and speeches are gathered by topic and arranged alphabetically.
  - Ackerman-Price-Anderson 1970 (Box 4)
  - AEC 1970 (Box 4)
  - Alternatives 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Cherry, Myron (testimony) 1971 (Box 4)
  - Consumers Power (documents) 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Costs vs. Benefits 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Davis-Besse Nuclear Power Station 1970 (Box 4)
  - Economics 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Action Council 1971 (Box 4)
  - Environment (miscellaneous) 1970 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Cost of Electric Power 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Fact Sheets 1970 (Box 4)
  - Fund Raising 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Gofman, J. W. 1970 (Box 4)
  - Great Lakes Fact Sheets 1970 (Box 4)
  - Heat Pollution 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Intervention 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - League of Women Voters Study 1971 (Box 5)
  - Legislative matters 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Lloyd Harbor Study Group 1971 (Box 5)
  - Midland AEC hearing 1970 (Box 5)
  - Midland Nuclear Plant (agency comments) 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota Documents 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - Morgan, Karl Z. 1970 (Box 5)
  - News clippings, Midland area 1970 (Box 5)
  - News clippings 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Open Lands and Resources 1970 (Box 5)
  - Palisades Nuclear Plant 1970 (Box 5)
  - Palisades Intervention 1970 (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Site Investigation 1967 (Box 5)
  - Savage, Bert 1970 (Box 5)
  - Shepherd, Jack 1971 (Box 5)
  - Sierra Club 1970 (Box 5)
  - State of Michigan 1970 (Box 5)
  - Student groups 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Saginaw Valley Nuclear Study Group 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Saginaw Valley College panel 1972 (Box 5)
  - Trout Unlimited 1971 (Box 5)
  - Water Resources (Michigan) 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Water Management (Regional planning) 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - Water Resources hearings 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Citizen Groups 1970-1996
  The Citizen Groups series (5.2 lin. ft.) documents the interlocking network of citizen environmental groups. By gathering and exchanging information, validating and celebrating each other's work, and providing templates and roadmaps for grassroots organizations addressing similar problems, these groups cooperated in advancing their environmental agenda. Materials included in these files include newsletters, correspondence, flyers, educational materials, and bibliographies. Don't Waste Michigan, the Saginaw Valley Nuclear Study Group, and the Sierra Club National Energy Committee were organizations through which Sinclair funneled her activism. The materials for the Great Lakes Energy Alliance are contained in a separate series, which follows.
  When Sinclair's work was funded by a grantmaker (such as the Sierra Club Foundation) she provided her benefactor with periodic summaries of how her work was progressing. These letters are a valuable resource because they provide a substantially contemporaneous account of Sinclair's successes, failures, and future plans.
  - American Friends Services Committee 1974-1979 (Box 5)
  - American Physical Society 1975 (Box 5)
  - Another Mother for Peace 1972-1977 (Box 5)
  - Arbor Alliance 1980 (Box 5)
  - Audubon Society 1975 (Box 5)
  - Business and Professional People for the Public Interest 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Canadian Citizens Groups 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Center for Science in the Public Interest (Washington, D.C.) 1976 (Box 6)
  - Chippewa Nature Center (Midland, MI) 1977 (Box 6)
  - Citizens Committee for Environmental Concern, Inc. 1971-1975 (Box 6)
  - Citizens Committee for Environmental Protection (Midland, MI) 1971-1975 (Box 6)
  - Citizens Committee for the Protection of the Environment (Ossining, NY) 1975 (Box 6)
  - Citizens Energy Council (Allendale, NJ) 1973-1982 (Box 6)
  - Citizens United for Responsible Energy (Des Moines, IA) 1974-1979 (Box 6)
  - Clamshell Alliance (Seabrook, NJ) 1977-1979 (Box 6)
  - Clear Creek (San Francisco, CA) 1971 (Box 6)
  - Coalition for Michigan 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Coalition for Safe Electric Power (Cleveland, OH) 1973-1976 (Box 6)
  - Committee for Conservation of Energy (Portland, OR) 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Land and Water (CLAW) (MSU Cooperative Extension) 1976 (Box 6)
  - Committee for Nuclear Responsibility, Inc. (New York, NY) 1972-1977 (Box 6)
  - Consumer Action Now, Inc. (CAN) (New York, NY) 1975 (Box 6)
  - Consumer Alliance of Michigan (Detroit, MI) 1974 (Box 6)
  - Council on Economic Priorities (New York, NY) 1977 (Box 6)
  - Critical Mass-"A Citizens Manual on Nuclear Energy 1974" (Box 6)
  - Critical Mass (Washington, DC) 1974-1980, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Dearborn Presbyterian Church 1976 (Box 6)
  - Detroit Area Coalition for the Environment (DACE) 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Eastern Federation of Nuclear Opponents and Safe Energy Proponents (State College, PA) 1976 (Box 6)
  - East Central Michigan Planning and Development Region (Essexville, MI) 1977 (Box 6)
  - East Lansing Peace Education Center 1980 (Box 6)
  - East Michigan Environmental Action Council (Birmingham, MI) 1975-1980 (Box 6)
  - Elements (Washington, DC) 1977-1979 (Box 6)
  - Energy and Environment Information Project (EEIP) (Wayne State University) 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Energy Daily (Washington, DC) 1976 (Box 6)
  - The Environment Communication Services (Traverse City, MI) 1976 (Box 6)
  - Environment Incorporated (Whitehall, MI) undated (Box 6)
  - Environmental Action (Washington, DC) 1972-1980 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Action (cont.) (Box 7)
  - Environmental Action for Survival (ENACT) (Ann Arbor, MI) 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Environmental Coalition on Nuclear Power (Jenkintown, PA) 1974-1976 (Box 7)
  - Environmental Defense Fund (East Setauket, NY) 1972-1976 (Box 7)
  - Environmental Directory (Box 7)
  - Environmental Policy Center (Washington, DC) 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Environmentalists for Full Employment (Washington, DC) 1979 (Box 7)
  - Federation of Atomic Scientists (FAS) (Washington, DC) 1971-1977 (Box 7)
  - Friends of the Earth (Washington, DC) 1972-1977 (Box 7)
  - Independent Phi Beta Kappa Environmental Study Group, New York, NY) 1970-1975 (Box 7)
  - Hudson Valley Citizens' Watch on Nuclear Safety (New Paltz, NY) 1971-1974 (Box 7)
  - Kalamazoo Nature Center 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Lake Michigan Federation (Chicago, IL) 1971-1976, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Lakeshore Gazette (Allendale, MI) 1977 (Box 7)